{
  "title": "People/Events in Period 2",
  "description": "Name who or what this event or person is.",
  "questions": [
    {
      "answer": "Jamestown",
      "question": "1st permanent English settlement in North America in 1607."
    },
    {
      "answer": "John Smith",
      "question": "A captain famous for world travel. As a young man, he took control in Jamestown. He organized the colony and saved many people from death the next winter and coined the phrase \"he who shall not work, shall not eat\". He also initiated attacks on Natives."
    },
    {
      "answer": "John Rolfe",
      "question": "He was one of the English settlers at Jamestown (and he married Pocahontas). He discovered how to successfully grow tobacco in Virginia and cure it for export, which made Virginia an economically successful colony. Eventually, he was killed in a Pequot attack."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Pocohontas",
      "question": "An American Indian princess who saved the life of John Smith and helped form more peaceful relations with the Powhatan when she married John Rolfe but died of smallpox in England on a visit to Rolfe's family. Her remains are still there as the English government refuses to send her remains back to North America."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Mayflower Compact",
      "question": "1620 - The first agreement for self-government in America. It was signed by the 41 men on the Mayflower and set up a government for the Plymouth colony"
    },
    {
      "answer": "John Winthrop",
      "question": "As governor of Massachusetts Bay Colony, Winthrop (1588-1649) was instrumental in forming the colony's government and shaping its legislative policy. He envisioned the colony, centered in present-day Boston, as a \"city upon a hill\" from which Puritans would spread religious righteousness throughout the world."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Puritans",
      "question": "A religious group who wanted to purify the Church of England. They came to America for religious freedom and settled Massachusetts Bay."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Pilgrims",
      "question": "These English Puritans who founded Plymouth colony in 1620"
    },
    {
      "answer": "New Amsterdam",
      "question": "A settlement established by the Dutch near the mouth of Hudson River and the southern end of Manhattan Island as a trade port for the Dutch trade empire."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Great Migration of Puritans",
      "question": "1630s- 70,000 refugees left England for New World increasing population of New England."
    },
    {
      "answer": "New York",
      "question": "It was founded by the Dutch for trade and furs and became an English Colony in 1664, when the English were determined to end Dutch trade dominance, and took over the colony without having to fire a shot."
    },
    {
      "answer": "House of Burgesses",
      "question": "1619 - The Virginia House of Burgesses formed, the first legislative body in colonial America. It was made up of two representatives from teach town voted on by men who owned property. Later other colonies would adopt the Houses of Burgesses concept creating self-governing bodies in the colonies."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Headright system",
      "question": "Headrights were parcels of land consisting of about 50 acres which were given to colonists who brought indentured servants into America. They were used by the Virginia Company to attract more colonists."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Indentured servants",
      "question": "Colonists who received free passage to North America in exchange for working without pay for a certain number of years"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Bacon's Rebellion",
      "question": "1676 - Nathaniel Bacon and other western Virginia settlers were angry at Virginia Governor Berkley for trying to appease the Doeg Indians after the Doegs attacked the western settlements. The frontiersmen formed an army, with Bacon as its leader, which defeated the Indians and then marched on Jamestown and burned the city. This rebellion ended suddenly when Bacon died of an illness. What was this rebellion?"
    },
    {
      "answer": "King Phillip's War",
      "question": "Under the leadership of Metacom, or King Phillip, the Wampanoag destroyed colonial towns, the colonists destroyed native farms, leading to the most deadly of Indian Wars. This war was disastrous for the natives leading to few surviving the war, and those that did left New England."
    },
    {
      "answer": "royal colony",
      "question": "Type of colony ruled by governors appointed by a king"
    },
    {
      "answer": "proprietary colony",
      "question": "Type of english colony in which the king gave land to proprietors in exchange for a yearly payment"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Salem Witch Trials",
      "question": "1629 outbreak of witchcraft accusations in a Puritan village marked by an atmosphere of fear, hysteria, and unfounded accusations in courts with Puritan ministers who served as judges. 19 women were executed."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Anne Hutcheson",
      "question": "One of the dissenters in Puritan Massachusetts held bible studies at her house and believed in a personal relationship with god. She moved to New Hampshire where she died along with her children from an Indian attack."
    },
    {
      "answer": "William Penn",
      "question": "Established the colony of Pennsylvania as a \"holy experiment\". Freemen had the right to vote, provided leadership for self- government based on personal virtues and Quaker religious beliefs. His colony was religiously tolerant leading to diversity in the region."
    },
    {
      "answer": "James Oglethorpe",
      "question": "Founded colony of Georgia as a chance for poor immigrants who were in debt to have a second chance at a comfortable life"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Dominion of New England",
      "question": "1686 - The British government combined the colonies of Massachusetts, Rhode Island, New Hampshire, and Connecticut into a single province headed by a royal governor (Edmund Andros). This Dominion ended in 1692, when the colonists revolted and drove out Governor Andros. What was the Dominion called?"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Navigation Acts",
      "question": "Three acts that regulated colonial trade and benefited England"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Mercantilism",
      "question": "An economic policy under which nations sought to increase their wealth and power by obtaining large amounts of gold and silver and by selling more goods than they bought."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Triangular Slave Trade",
      "question": "A practice, primarily during the eighteenth century, in which European ships transported slaves from Africa to Caribbean islands, molasses from the Caribbean to Europe, and trade goods from Europe to Africa."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Middle Passage",
      "question": "A voyage that brought enslaved Africans across the Atlantic Ocean to North America and the West Indies. The conditions on the ships from Africa to the west led to the loss of hundreds of thousands of lives."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Social mobility",
      "question": "Movement of individuals or groups from one position in a society's stratification system to another"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Great Awakening",
      "question": "(1730s and 1740s) Religious movement characterized by emotional preaching. It established American religious precedents such as camp meetings, revivals, and a \"born again\" philosophy."
    },
    {
      "answer": "French & Indian War",
      "question": "1754 - 1763; conflict between France and Great Britain over land in North America in the Ohio River Valley."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Battle of Quebec",
      "question": "(1759) British victory over French forces on the outskirts of Quebec."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Ohio River Valley",
      "question": "Controversial land that led to the French and Indian War; British win war and claim this land; region where British fur traders went; rich soil for farming."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Join or Die",
      "question": "Famous cartoon drawn by Ben Franklin which encouraged the colonies to join in fighting the British during the French and Indian War"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Albany Plan of Union",
      "question": "Plan proposed by Benjamin Franklin that sought to unite the 13 colonies for trade, military, and other purposes; the plan was turned down by the colonies & the Crown."
    }
  ]
}